Guide to the Bernard Berlyn Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bernard Berlyn papers
1884-1930
MS 1005
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The papers of Bernard Berlyn consist largely of birthday greetings (1921-1928), including a holograph letter from Eugene V. Debs. There are also photographs, lectures, autobiographical reminiscences, clippings on Chicago socialist activities, and miscellaneous printed matter.
Berlyn, Bernard, 1843-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Bernard Berlyn estate.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Bernard (Barney) Berlyn was born in Amsterdam, Holland on February 7, 1843. In 1850 his family emigrated to the United States and settled in New York City. After finishing primary school, Berlyn became a cigar maker, and joined the first cigar maker's union in 1863.
In the same year, he moved to Chicago where he became active in the Chicago Federation of Labor. A life-long member of the Socialist Party, Berlyn was a candidate for Congress on the Socialist ticket in several elections. In 1913 he ran for the senate and was the first socialist candidate to receive votes in Illinois. He was also a member of the national executive committee of the socialist party from 1901-07, a national committee man from 1901-08, and a delegate to the national conventions of 1904, 1908, 1912, and 1920.
Berlyn's work as a labor organizer brought him into contact with Clarence Darrow, Norman Thomas, Eugene V. Debs, Lucy Parsons, and other liberal leaders. He was co-author, with William S. McGuire, of the book Why Workers Should Join the Socialist Party.
Barney Berlyn died in 1928 at the age of eighty-five.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Bernard Berlyn consist largely of birthday greetings (1921-1928), including a holograph letter from Eugene V. Debs. There are also photographs, lectures, autobiographical reminiscences, clippings on Chicago socialist activities, and miscellaneous printed matter.
Socialism; Chicago (Ill.) -- Politics and government; Berlyn, Bernard, 1843-1928; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926
- Inventory
  - Correspondence and financial items, 1884-1886, 1925-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Debs, Eugene, 1921 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Debs, Theodore, 1921 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autobiographical and biographical writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Birthday greetings
    - 1921
      General
      See: Box 2
    - 1923-1928 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 8)
  - Writings and teaching
    - Two essays on socialism, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notes on Capital, v. 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorabilia, 1922, 1930, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Obituary notices, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters of condolence, 1928 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pierce, Paul [organizer 7th Ward Socialist Party (Chicago) and brother-in-law]: writings, [ca. 1903] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Socialist Party: miscellaneous items from Chicago, [ca. 1924] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    General note
    See also: Folder 13
  - Miscellaneous printed matter on socialism, 1901-1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Socialist newspapers
    - Chicago Leader, 1925 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - English Section Forward, 1927 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - New York Call, 1921 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Socialist Worker, 1922 December (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper clippings, [ca. 1904-1905] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Birthday greetings, 1921 (Box 2)